wow
uh
[Music]
hello everybody
how are you all doing i hope you're
doing very well welcome to the 51st live
episode of ask abidjit
and it's great to be back with you all
this is one of the best parts of my week
to do these live shows and meet you face
to face virtually
so today we're gonna do a live chat
session live chat q a from the live chat
that you are putting in the box
and tomorrow we will do a video chat
so today it's on live chat so let me see
who all is there with us today
i can see shubham kareem pradeep pandey
niraj kumar singh prithviram
ashok
and everybody else
great to see you all great to see you
all thank you for being here
so what shall we discuss today as always
it is you the viewers who are going to
drive this q a session
so
ask me your questions let's see what
questions have already been asked and
let us begin
with
that
raghav sharma says if you support the
oit the out of india theory how do you
explain the fundamental
linguistic differences between north
indian languages and south indian
languages all right raghav you said
there are fundamental linguistic
differences what
fundamental linguistic differences do we
have
do you mean the fundamental linguistic
differences that the europeans have told
us exist i mean it is the europeans the
british colonizers of india who
classified
india's languages in two major groups
the indo-aryan languages and the
dravidian languages
it was the bishop
the christian missionary the bishop
robert caldwell who studied one language
tamil
rudimentarily
and then on the basis of his
fragmentary understanding of one
language he created an entire language
family out of it called the dravidian
language family and he classified all of
southern india's languages into this
dravidian language family which he
created and today everybody blindly
follows this
this dogma every indian scholar every
indian intellectual every indian
academic professor teacher
lecturer
and so on so forth they all blindly
follow the dogma created by the bishop
robert caldwell
well
has anybody in india any any genuine
linguist tried to understand
the languages
a priori
using first principles analysis instead
of going by the accepted dogma of
created by bishop robert caldwell no
because if you if if you
even have a very basic understanding of
southern indian languages you will find
that there are lots of words
there is a significant
percentage of these of the words of the
vocabulary of these southern indian
languages that actually originates in
sanskrit
telugu is almost 40 to 50
sanskrit vocabulary kannada very similar
tamil has 30 or 40 sanskrit vocabulary
malayalam is very sanskritized and so on
and so forth tulu
and so on and so forth every single
southern indian language has a very
significant percentage of sanskrit
origin words and there are many
words from these languages that are
present in northern indian languages as
well
and so on
so you know what
it is we are taught that everything is
black and white north indian and south
indian indo-aryan was a dravidian and so
on but nobody has bothered to do a
proper a priori first principles
analysis of this in either in the 20th
century or in the 21st century we are
simply blindly following this dogma
which was given to us by our british
masters and these are the fundamental
linguistic differences that raghav you
are speaking about i do not blame you
for believing it this is what you have
been taught this is what we have all
been taught and the education system
breaks destroys our curiosity it it
prevents it it makes us lose the ability
to think
on our own
it it destroys the ability of every
student to use their own intelligence
which they all have and that's why we
simply blindly follow everything they're
taught
and that's what we see here
so
my answer to this is that yes there are
the
linguistic landscape in india is
incredibly complex
india is the original founder's zone of
the out of africa migration humans
settled in india at least 65 or 70
thousand years ago and these languages
have been evolving right here in the
subcontinent for that long a period of
time so we are going to have to do a
proper a priori linguistic analysis
starting from zero
if we want to understand
what india's linguistics really are
where do they originate
how many language families do we
actually have
are these so-called dravidian languages
and so-called indo-aryan languages are
they actually a separate language family
because we know that genetically we are
very much the same
indians all of us
northern india southern india eastern
india west india and so on
right
so we are very much the same
genetically
our genetics are 65 70 000 years old
and i would say that india's linguistics
also would be that old
so we need to do a proper a priori
linguistic analysis
we need to stop relying on these 19th
century colonial
dogmas
and therefore i do not agree one bit
that there are fundamental linguistic
differences between
indian languages very in various parts
of india there are
obviously there's going to be some
differences but what is the origin of
these differences and more than
differences we have similarities i mean
how do you explain all the similarities
you can't right so that's the thing
there is no black and white right or
wrong in this
what i can tell you is that everything
these people have tried to impose upon
us
is incorrect
i want to see
an indian institute of fundamental
linguistics wherein the brightest young
minds of india
are brought together
and we can have a 20 30 50 year project
to uncover the truth about india's
linguistics so that's what needs to
happen right so i do support the oit the
out of india theory it is very well
established by now in science in
genetics that india is the original out
of india out of africa founder zone it
is out of the indian subcontinent that
humans migrated all across eurasia and
eventually to other continents
and there were there were even back
migrations into africa which is why you
find indian origin r1b genetics in the
heart of africa as well today
so the truth is way more complex
than what than the way it is portrayed
we need
to start looking at things afresh from a
scientific perspective
we need to start looking at the actual
heart data instead of believing other
people's opinions so that's what i would
invite all of you
to do
right let us see some more questions
let us see some more questions what else
do we have
here's an interesting question about us
about
the search for extraterrestrial
intelligence
so sagnik asks please tell us about the
nature of the wow signal was this
singular event a real signal if so what
was its origin this is a very
interesting question now this is
something i had read about about a
decade or so ago
that uh we there is this uh project
called the seti project in
in the united states the search for
extraterrestrial intelligence and there
are these arrays of
radio telescopes that scan the sky and
look for
interesting
radio
signals from outer space now radio waves
are just a form of electromagnetic
radiation light is electromagnetic
radiation and so on
so they scan
the um
the scan the cosmos and look for
interesting signals now what's an
interesting signal you know the the
cosmos the space outer space is full of
noise in the electromagnetic spectrum
you have all kinds of noise coming from
galaxies uh noise that's produced by
pulsars by magnetars
by quasars and various astrophysical
objects which
give off electromagnetic radiation in a
variety of frequencies
many of which are radio frequencies and
therefore when they first found
the the first evidence of of uh
what was it was it pulsars pulsars
pulsars are those very rapidly spinning
stars millisecond pulsar and so on so
you found this extraordinary
uh
regular
pulses of radio waves which
initially astronomers believed that only
intelligent beings could produce such
signals but eventually it was found that
these are actually astrophysical objects
called pulsars and millisecond pressures
and so on and there are lots of other
astrophysical phenomena that give rise
to radio waves so the cosmos is an
extremely
noisy
source radio source electromagnetic
source and yet
we are searching for
certain signals that could only be
produced by intelligent life
so signals they don't repeat and there
are and have certain characteristics so
i think sometime in the 1970s there was
this one signal that was captured
and it was incredible i don't remember
exactly what it was like but uh
it was
very unique and it was it it had the
distinct characteristics of
a signal that cannot only be produced by
an intelligent uh
being civilization
so on
so the person who was uh manning the uh
the night shift in one of those one of
these uh
observatories saw the signal and
scribbled down wow next to it
now
i'm not sure if it's been adequately
explained or not i do not think it has
been adequately explained by any natural
phenomenon thus far and unfortunately
that signal has never repeated itself so
the portion the place the the location
in the night sky in the sky
where it came from
uh people have been uh scientists have
been trying to scan that that location
for a very long period of time and
nothing else has ever come out of it now
i am not sure if it has been
conclusively proven to be something that
originated from a natural astrophysical
source but it's something which is i
don't think they have been able to
conclusively prove that
so i think
as far as i know that it is still
not proven or not not determined where
what what is the origin of this signal
and that's why it is one of the most
intriguing
and interesting and exciting phases
uh episodes of of uh scientific history
astrophysics uh astronomical history and
the history of the search of search for
extraterrestrial intelligence
so uh
i don't have the exact answer as to
whether it has been proven to be
physical natural or extraterrestrial i
think it's still
it's still in the superposition of both
but yeah it's it's a very interesting
episode
and uh
and they're still scanning the sky for
more such signals i mean you may recall
there was this uh
a couple of years away two or three
years ago there was the star that they
found which underwent these drastic
episodes of dimming and dimming down and
brightening up again uh it was
discovered by a researcher by a team of
researchers led by tabetha boyan
it was called tabi's star and
it was
seriously being considered that this
could be the dimming the sudden dimming
episodes of the star could be perhaps
possibly caused by
a mega structure a an artificial mega
structure a dyson sphere of sorts
a dyson
ensemble of of some kind
so that
today it is believed in the past two
three years they have come to the
conclusion the conclusion that this
could have been caused possibly by a
swarm of large orbiting bodies perhaps
comets
but even that doesn't seem 100
uh
conclusive
and there are and they have now
discovered some other stars too that
that exhibit such
strange
non-regular
brightening and darkening episodes so we
are
we are entering an interesting
phase of observational astronomy and
especially the search for
extraterrestrial intelligence as our
instruments get better as we are able to
actually take photographs of planets
around other stars exoplanets and so on
we are going to make more discoveries
and maybe we may actually discover
something really interesting
like uh
the signal of life the signature of life
somewhere else on a non-solar system
world it is certainly possible
so
interesting times
okay karthik shaniva says can you please
explain the first principles thinking
first principles thinking is
when you
uh
okay what is first principles thinking
it's when you examine when you analyze
a problem
not on the basis of other people's
opinions
but looking at the actual source of the
phenomenon for instance
last week i had a gentleman
a nice guy actually who asked me about
who was or a little argumentative i
don't blame him it's okay
uh he was talking about the uh
caa
uh and the farmer's protests and uh
and all that and he was saying that
i have heard from other sources other
channels that it is very much
anti-farmer and the ca is also
anti-national and so on
so
that is
an example of unfortunately dogmatic
thinking when you are basing your
opinions
on the product of other people's
thinking
so you saw some youtube videos
from two three channels and they all say
that this is bad for the country this is
anti-farmer so you believe you believe
what they are saying and you form your
opinion based on other people's thought
processes that is called dogmatic
thinking because dog dogma means you are
using the results the products of other
people's
thoughts
first principle thinking means you
ignore what other people are saying
and you look at the actual farm bill
that is the source of the entire
controversy you examine the the former
the the new law yourself
it is available in the public domain
and then you form your own opinion based
on the law written down in black and
white whether it is good for the farmers
or bad for the farmers that is called
first principles thinking and again when
it comes to uh science
etc
first principles thinking is that you
take the basics the fundamental laws of
nature of mathematics and physics
to form your opinions rather than
basing your opinions on the opinions of
other scientists
on the conclusions that other scientists
have made
let me give you another example there
are right now
as of today many uh i have heard
uh i have seen lots of comments
by many of you
saying that so-and-so researcher has
determined the date of the mahabharata
or the date of the ramayana etc and
some of you seem to be very very
strongly convinced by that right
now here is the fact
as of to see here's the the scientific
methodology
when i
do some research
and i come to a conclusion i'm going to
check my research recheck my work
recheck my entire process a few times
and when i'm convinced that i have not
made any mistake when that my
conclusions my analysis my my
calculations are correct then i'm going
to make a claim that this is what i have
discovered right so this is a claim that
i have made now for the claim to be
proven it has to be
replicated
independently by at least two other
teams of scientists
only when they are able to replicate the
same result that i have
i have found only then can my k claim
be said to be proven
so if one person
does some research for five years ten
years twenty years whatever however long
it takes and comes to a conclusion it is
not proven my friends
and if you believe that person and you
say this is the date of the mahabharata
or the ramayana that is dogmatic
thinking it is not first principle
thinking because you don't know
what process what methodology he or she
has used
to come to these conclusions and find
these dates
you are not i would assume
an expert in astronomy
and in all these astronomical
calculations so on what basis are you
believing the person i am not i am not
by by any means saying that so and so
claim is right or so and so claim is
wrong or so and so person is good or bad
i am not saying any of that
i am simply making the fundamental point
that you are basing your underst your
your opinion
on something that is not scientific on
something that is not proven so that is
called dogmatic thinking you just
blindly believe what somebody is
claiming
that has not been proven independently
by other researchers yet
and therefore it is not proven
so so these are some of the ways that
these are some of the uh intellectual
fallacies and pitfalls that we have
and
the the antidote to that is first
principles thinking now i don't expect
all of you or most of you to have any
understanding of astronomy why should
you have it it's not your profession
it's fine
so in that case you should not believe
the claim that has been put forth until
other researchers are able to
corroborate it
and then
once it is corroborated by at least two
teams of researchers then you can
believe it so that is the scientific
process for instance
in 1915 when albert einstein put forth
the general theory of relativity no one
cared
nobody cared
only a few years later when it was
actually proven when his predictions
were demonstrably proven
it's only then that he became a
celebrity so one must wait for these
claims to be proven one cannot blindly
start believing things
so that is the scientific process there
is the way to think in a scientific
manner and that is first principle
thinking by going to the root of the
matter instead of relying on other
people's opinions okay that was a very
long answer let's go on to something
else i hope that makes sense
all right karan asks what is meritocracy
is it better than democracy and is it
even possible it is certainly possible
it has been it has existed in the past
in india it has existed in the past in
other civilizations cultures empires and
so on it is certainly possible
it is very much a component of democracy
in any
uh in a proper democracy you would have
meritocracy meritocracy is very simple
if you you have an opening for a certain
position let's say you let's say the
indian army needs 10 000 new soldiers
right let's say
the indian army the indian armed forces
are in need
of 10 000 new soldiers
so
what is meritocracy in this case
uh
what kind of so i mean
and let's say a hundred thousand
individuals apply
for these openings of the ten thousand
so one out of ten has to be selected
right because a hundred thousand have
applied but only 10 000 posts are
available so then you going to have an
examination fitness training firearms
training and all that and you are going
to evaluate their skills and their
aptitude and their potential
and then you are supposed to choose the
best 10 000 out of those hundred
thousand that is called meritocracy
okay
now
on what basis will you choose the best
soldiers the best candidates based on
how physically fit and strong they are a
soldier's job
is to undergo hardships
the soldier's job is not to give up his
life or for the for the country it is to
ensure that the enemy has to give up his
life for his country so
these are the factors that uh are to be
considered and the soldiers have to be
efficient killing machines they have to
be ruthless they have to be able to be
calm under pressure under stress and so
on so there are certain mental factors
that have to be considered physical
factors that have to be considered what
sort of endurance does a person have
what sort of stamina does he have
how fast can he run and so on so forth
is a good marksman
is he
cold-minded enough to be able to kill
the enemy when it's required and so on
so there's a number of factors you to
consider and you have to pick up the ten
thousand best soldiers then the ten
thousand best candidates out of one
hundred thousand that is called
meritocracy
now if you start considering
factors like
what quota do they fall under
is it a minority quota is it a
cst quota is it some other reservation
quota that destroys the entire concept
of meritocracy
because then
it doesn't matter whether you're good or
not at your job what really matters is
what quota you belong to and that is the
death of meritocracy and that is what
you see in india's education system in
the india's governance system in all the
job applications in the government
and i'm not sure if it's there in the
armed forces also but it should not be
the entire country if it has to do well
should be on the basis of merit only the
person who is best suited for the job
should be given the job
whether you are a cop whether you are a
government officer whether you are a
judge whether you are a soldier even
while in in promotions
the best have to be promoted not the
most politically connected and so on so
that is the difference between
meritocracy and and whatever else it is
whatever else it is is called corruption
and india's system is deeply corrupt
because there is no concept of
meritocracy
whether it is entry into the iits or any
uh indian government-run
uh education institutions whether it is
entry into
into the government services into the
bureaucracy or whatever else and so on
and so forth so that is
what is the exact opposite
of meritocracy and a system in which you
have complete transparency and complete
meritocracy is going to give you the
best possible
workers the best possible leaders
in the in the country will do well and a
system in which you don't have this
is going to produce mediocrity and decay
and corruption which is what you see in
india today
so that is the difference between
meritocracy and whatever else and
corruption
and
anti-meritocracy
so it is very much a part of democracy
in india's democracy we don't have it so
india's democracy is deeply flawed
and it is not really a democracy see it
is certainly possible it is certainly
possible if you see the mongol empire it
came out of nowhere
it came out of nowhere in just 20 30
years one man ching is khan built an
empire out of nothing
and it was so successful because it was
purely meritocratic
so it's possible it is certainly
possible and it should be
implemented
if you want your country your
civilization your culture to do well
right let's take some more questions
shrikant says can india beat the chinese
economy in the long run historically
over the past five how long has china
existed three thousand three and a half
thousand years
historically throughout the entire
duration of china's existence as a
culture and a civilization india's
economy has been bigger than china's
economy it's only in the past 500 or so
years that india went down it decayed
because it was smashed into pieces by
the british occupiers and before that
the turkic occupiers of india who
plundered and destroyed india
and uh
you know yeah that's what happened
so india's historical position has been
at the top of the world's
economic hierarchy india has always been
throughout throughout its history the
largest the greatest
the most prosperous economy in the world
china has historically ever ever since
it has existed in the past three and a
half thousand years or so china has
historically been number two
can india beat the chinese economy in
the long run well it is in our blood and
in our nature to be number one
right now we are going through a bad
phase it takes a little bit of time when
i say a little bit of time i mean 50 to
100 years so don't expect this to happen
overnight
hopefully in our lifetimes hopefully in
the next 20 30 years i would like to see
india surpass china it is very much
very much possible india has all the
potential in the world
india needs the right leadership
hopefully we are on the right track so
it is very much very much possible
okay let's uh let's take some more
questions
hello curious minds hello hello it's
nice to see all the curious minds
okay some questions are being repeated
um
okay some more question
there's a guy manish says there's a guy
who says ram say to being man-made
doesn't prove doesn't prove ramayana to
be true
with the argument that new york is real
doesn't mean that spider-man exists
well there's no point even arguing with
such people
all right
see
the thing is this
in the ramayana there is a very specific
depiction
in spider-man comics there is no
depiction of new york city being built
right
spider-man exists in this fictitious new
york or whatever place it is
in the spider-man mythos in the
spider-man mythology there is no
depiction
of people getting together and building
new york city if that was the case then
the spider-man comics would prove that
it was real because new york exists and
so on but in the ramayana there is a
very clear specific detailed depiction
of how this bridge was built between
india and sri lanka
and it was
all this time considered to be a myth
but now it it very much appears that
it's a man-made
uh man-made structure
i think the indian government has now
shown some interest in i think
some archaeological work is being done i
believe
which will conclusively prove it one day
or the other what is the origin of the
rama sethu bridge
so let us wait for a little bit of time
if it is man-made then where else is it
shown in the entire history of the world
or where else is it depicted as being
built only in one place in the ramayana
so
that's what it is
so this is the logical logical fallacy
fallacy that is being done we are
putting the card before the horse you
know
so there's no point arguing with such
people or even debating such people who
don't understand what logic is
bhanu prakash shukla has been asking me
a question for a very long time okay i'm
glad i saw it this time
this is about nilesh oaks research paper
like the timings
of the mahabharata ramen he depicted the
astronomer astronomical facts over there
what's your take my take is very simple
nilesh oak has done an enormous amount
of work
i think he has invested 10 or 20 years
in this that is incredibly
commendable
to invest such a large part of your life
in doing this work and he has come up
with some dates of the ramayana in the
mahabharata
my point is very simple i really
appreciate the work he has done
it needs to be independently verified
and proven by other teams of researchers
until this happens
one cannot claim
that this is 100 correct
like i said albert einstein's theory of
relativity which he put forth in 1915
was completely ignored until it was
proven
by experimental physicists about five or
six years later i think it was in 1920
or 21 that it was actually proven to be
correct one of his predictions the
bending of light around large objects
was experimentally proven and that's
when he became a celebrity that's when
the theory of relativity was actually
accepted and therefore any such claim
that is put forth see even albert
einstein toiled away
alone
okay for for about for about an entire
decade to come up with this theory of
relativity it was a labor of love it was
a very lonely effort
and yet it was not accepted until it was
properly proven by experimental
physicist by others other than him
therefore i really appreciate what mr
nileshok has done i really commend the
effort he's put in but to be accepted
his work has to be independently
corroborated by at least one or two
other teams of researchers the entire
uh all the calculations all the claims
all the all the various claims that he
has made they all need to be proven and
corroborated that is the scientific
process
that is the scientific process it's the
only way
one can actually accept a new claim that
has been made because his work is
scientific work it's based on astronomy
so it has to be proven independently by
other researchers so that is my take on
this
i really appreciate the occasion if it
is proven to be correct
if it is proven
to be correct by independent researchers
i think he deserves a padma award for
what he has done but it has to be
independently verified by other
researchers until that time we cannot
make the claim that this has been proven
right it is as of now just a claim it is
not
proven
i hope that answers the question
okay uh some questions are being asked
multiple times please don't do that
please ask your question only once
okay otherwise it's like spam it's
not fun
right let's see some more questions let
us see some more questions
thanos thanos asks okay thanos is
talking to raghav sharma if you see
europe everyone speaks different
languages
yet when it comes to western
civilizational supremacy all of them
unite under one roof i wonder why that
can't happen in india it can happen in
india if there's a good if there's a
strong enough leadership
it can happen it can certainly happen it
has happened in the past india has been
unified an entire subcontinent sized
civilization unified under one
leadership multiple times it can once
again happen in the future one needs
to unify a country as large as india
which is as big as the european union
even larger when it comes to population
when it comes to unifying that so that a
civilization of that size
you need a once in a thousand years kind
of leader
so that is what we wait for that's what
we await we need that kind of leadership
who can
who can bend the entire country to his
or her will
and unify the civilization once again
after a thousand years the last time it
happened was
well to some extent it happened under
the great raj raj and rajendra chola the
chola dynasty who unified southern india
with the entirety of southeast asia all
the way to the philippines under one
cultural and civilizational umbrella
before that it happened during the the
gupta empire
samudragupta and etc i think the
karkotas
also did that sort of thing you had
among
an emperor who lived for about who ruled
for about 60 plus years who unified a
large part of india you had kanishka the
great who unified much of india and much
of central asia as well
and before that you had the mauryan
dynasty chandragupta mori etc who
unified india so we need that sort of
leadership mediocre little politicians
are not going to unify in india i am not
pointing my fingers at any specific
individual when i say mediocre
politicians 99 of politicians are
mediocre
we do have some very good leaders in
this country
the question is how great
are they
are they willing to be
so let's see let's wait and watch
i think that we are doing better than
before much better than before
but one must always demand more from
one's leaders
so it's all about leadership it is
certainly possible
right let's take some more questions
okay some people are asking 17 questions
in one how to answer that
just ask me one question each and then
that we will take it that way
right
tuber asks
did indians have a sense of indian ness
if yes then why didn't the good gurjara
palace rashtrikuta's liberate sindh from
the arabs rather than fighting with each
other for connors please answer it's all
about the leadership
there there is there has always been a
sense of indian-ness whether you go to
the east of india bengal bangla pradesh
bangladesh whether you go to kalinga
whether you go to the southern parts of
india the cholas the pandyas the cheras
etc
the gangas whether they go north east
west wherever they we have always had
one overarching culture one overarching
civilizational language
we have a lot of diversity a lot of
plurality our culture manifests itself
in so many different ways and yet it is
just one overarching culture which you
see even across southeast asia the same
traditions
the same culture
until recently so yes there has always
been a sense of indian-ness so why
didn't the gurjaras the palace rashford
et cetera liberates in the from arabs
rather than fighting for kanoj because
they were small mediocre kings
there was no great king who could unify
the country in the civilization the way
the mauryas did it the way kanishka the
great did
the way the guptas did the way the
cholas did and so on
they were not that great
in terms of leadership
right
when one great leader emerges
he or she is capable of unifying the
entire country imagine
in the 13th century the state of
mongolia a bunch of rag tagged nomadic
tribes fighting each other for the
scraps of the land and then one boy was
born there
whose name was tebujin he grew up
and unified the entire country and
conquered more than half the world
it happened in in in a matter of a few
decades
in just 20
20 to 23 years
this man chingus
conquered more territory
than more than 30 roman empires could do
in 300 years
so it's possible when you have that sort
of leadership anything is possible so at
this time that you are talking about
when the gurjaras palace and russia and
various other little mediocre kings were
fighting for small territories it's
because they were mediocre kings they
were mediocre leaders
had there been a great leader
we would have been
free of the arabs and sindh would have
been
well
indianized all over again
and saved from the invaders so that's
that's the thing it's all about
leadership it's always about leadership
when you have the light right leadership
when you have strong enough leadership
everything is possible nothing is
impossible
but when you have mediocre leaders
when you have
leaders who believe in
in rent seeking and fighting for little
scraps that's when the country goes to
hell
like it has
been
in the past millennium the past one
thousand years of humiliation
okay some more questions
says ambedkar wrote that gita was copied
from buddhist texts is it true i am not
aware of
see listen i have not really studied mr
ambedkar
i don't know what he has written so i
can't answer this question really
and i so i'm not sure if he actually
wrote this or did not write it
if anybody has made the claim
that the gita was copied from buddhist
texts it is absolute utter nonsense
okay nefarious human asks would chennai
super kings have won the indian premier
league had they played during the vedic
period i think
there would have been other teams during
the vedic period they would have been
singapore united there would have been
uh
let me see hastinapur united inder
uh tuskars would have been there
hastinaput tusks
means the city of elephants right so
hastina put taskers indira indraprasth
united there would have been uh vanga
the the our team from vanga pradesh also
and many many other teams so i'm not
sure that chennai super kings would have
had the ammunition and the firepower
given their team of old guys
to actually have when won the ipl
and of course you would have had
different weapons the brahmastra and
other things would come into play you
know so i don't think chennai super
kings would have won the ipl
had they played during the vedic period
it would have been a very different kind
of tournament at the time
so yeah good question good question
aniket asks how is mathematics used in
deriving scientific theories so then to
answer that i have to explain what is
mathematics
see mathematics
is
the language of
physics mathematics expresses the
patterns and regularities of nature in
an abstract language in the most concise
form
possible
so it expresses
the regularities and patterns that we
find throughout
nature
and it is a property of the entire
universe and therefore using mathematics
sitting right here in my study room
i can derive
the laws that govern the entire universe
if i am intelligent enough to do that
using simply mathematics
so that is the power of mathematics
so what you do is you do first
principles thinking
right you observe the universe
and
based on the observations
you try to write down the regularities
and patterns that you observe
and that eventually takes the form of
fundamental physical laws
and then you use those laws to derive
other
uh to to to derive other
regularities and patterns of nature
and to find the uh
find
what is common between certain laws for
instance we have one upon
our pattern that exists not only in
gravitation but also in electromagnetism
and so on and so on so forth
so that is the reason why mathematics is
an integral
central part of physics
you cannot have physics i mean you can
try to express the regularities and
patterns of nature in the form of words
but then it would take paragraphs
and pages to describe what can be
described in just one line using
mathematics right and again if you use
language then it is imprecise
mathematics is completely precise
so that is what mathematics says and
that is why it is used in deriving
scientific theories because it expresses
patterns and regularities of nature that
are found throughout the universe not
only not just on our planet
so that's how we are able to discover
new physics
new laws of nature and so on so forth
using simply mathematics and the power
of observational data
all right let's see some more questions
uh ashish says i love physics it seems
very interesting but i don't like doing
numericals what should i do see you
cannot do physics without mathematics
mathematics is at the core of physics it
is the language of physics you simply
cannot progress beyond a certain stage
in physics if you don't do mathematics
and i understand that you don't like
doing numericals because i'm sure that
you had very bad teachers who did not
teach you mathematics properly this is
the story with every single student in
india
most
indian students they end up hating
mathematics because their teachers are
so
incompetent
and because they're not taught
mathematics properly during the
foundational stages if you don't
understand basic arithmetic properly if
you're not taught basic arithmetic
properly then you can never learn higher
mathematics like algebra trigonometry
geometry calculus and so on so forth
right it's impossible
if the foundation of the building is bad
then you simply can't progress further
and the building crumbles
so i understand why you don't like doing
numericals
and problems and all that because you
you probably had you very likely had
very poor teachers
so if you really want to pursue physics
seriously then you need to revisit your
mathematical knowledge
go back to the mathematics of your
school stage find out where your
deficiencies are and just
just
iron them out by doing
easier problems and so on mathematics is
actually extraordinarily simple it's
incredibly simple if you are taught
properly step by step
it's the simplest thing easiest thing in
the world if you understand the
fundamentals then you can easily make
the progress to higher stages
so that's the deal you cannot
progress
in physics
without being good at math
so that's the only option you have if
you really want to take it seriously
all right let's take some more question
questions
akshay says
how are the mossad of israel so fearless
carrying out assassinations in other
countries well the mossad see israel is
a very different kind of country
compared to india
india
israel has a very uh
it is in a very interesting position
in
western asia
it's on the eastern coast of the
mediterranean sea it is surrounded on
all sides by enemy countries
uh so let's take a look at the look at
the map shall we let's take a look at
the map and see exactly where it is
because if you see the map then you'll
understand what the deal is
so you know what geography plays a very
significant and very important role
in geopolitics and in shaping a nation's
nation's psyche and ethos and all that
so let's take a look at
the map
here is the map
so this here is israel as you can see to
the south you have egypt
the west you have jordan
over here you to
to the east you have jordan sorry
over here you have saudi arabia
to the north east you have syria to the
north you have lebanon
nearby you have turkey and so on and so
forth all enemy countries
and even if you go further east you have
iran and then you have pakistan
etc all of these countries wish to see
israel wiped off the map they are all
enemies they want to see israel
destroyed dead and buried
and yet israel has
has
managed to not just survive they have
managed to thrive
so
it's because
the country is always has always been in
this precarious position they have been
attacked a number of times they have
faced
physical extinction physical destruction
a number of times
they know that
their survival is always in danger
and that's why
they have a very peculiar attitude they
have this
they have the shin bet which is the
internal security of
apparatus and then they have the mossad
which is which is a colloquial informal
informal term
which is the external
intelligence apparatus and
agency so the mossad it's its objective
is to promote and further in israel's
national interests
beyond the boundaries of israel by
carrying out covert operations
assassinations when it's required
and ensuring that israel's enemies are
targeted wherever they are in the world
and this is possible only if the
political class of israel supports this
sort of activity and the political class
in israel has always been very
nationalistic and it's always been very
clear
about the fact that they should do this
another country which is like this is
iran which does carry out lots of
clandestine activities way beyond iran's
political boundaries
iran carries out
various activities within the
territory of iraq in syria as well
in uh in
yemen i believe
in afghanistan too and so on so iran
also
does a lot of such clandestine
activities
beyond its boundaries
uh so so these are two countries that do
that israel of course does it globally
they have even captured
former nazis from south america from
argentina adolf aikman was captured in
argentina in the 1960s he was kidnapped
and brought all the way to israel by the
mossad where he was
well where he underwent a trial and he
was eventually executed for his crimes
against humanity
so
the reason why the mossad is able to do
all this is because they have full
complete political support they are
given all the resources
they need
and because israel also has a very good
startup ecosystem all the latest
technology and so on which enables them
to carry out these operations with
greater ease
so it's all about the mindset
now when it comes to india
we don't carry out assassinations abroad
of our enemies abroad india has plenty
of enemies outside of india in pakistan
and other countries as well india has
never ever taken any action against them
that we know of at least not in the way
the israelis or the iranians do and even
within india there are so many
anti-national activities happening and
nothing is i mean
much of it just goes on
with a great deal of impudence
so india is a very different country
compared to israel india is
nowhere near as ruthless in pursuing its
national interest
in comparison with israel so the reason
why the mossad is so fearless and so
capable is that it has complete the
complete support of the political class
so that's the main reason
right let's take some more
interesting questions
aniket says can mathematics be used to
communicate
verbally
well
only if everybody understands
mathematics and that too you cannot
convey certain things like emotions and
things like that
mathematically there's no mathematics to
do there's no equation that that
represents various emotions and feelings
and and so on so forth so that's why we
need
verbal speech that's why we need
language which is much more evocative
and which has much more nuance
it is a whole different uh
thing that is being communicated right
so when you're talking about the laws of
nature
human language doesn't work you have to
use mathematics but when it comes to
communication in the human sphere in in
societal uh in the societal sense etc
mathematics simply cannot work
so that's the thing because see
mathematics like i said it expresses the
patterns and regularities of nature
it cannot express the patterns and
regularities of human emotions and
social
social uh connections and all that
because
these things are very subjective
there are no patterns there humans are
very irrational
from time to time many of us us are
quite irrational
there may be patterns etc but those
patterns we have never been able to
decipher
right
so unfortunately mathematics doesn't
work in that case it only works when it
comes to the laws of nature not to the
not when it comes to to the laws of
interpersonal communication and human
nature and consciousness and all that
that is a totally different thing which
we still don't understand
right
all right let's take some more questions
venkatasai asks what can replace
democracy in bharat something which is
native what type of governance it should
be
and when does the partitioned land of
bharath you reunite okay a number of
questions let me answer democracy
democracy originated in bharat it
originated in the indian subcontinent
it is very well recorded it
during the mahajanapada era we had a
hybrid form of democracy we had kings
and members but they were duty-bound
they were dharma bound to to to obey
the will of the people
and the will of their of their advisory
council and so on so the advisory
council and the people could override
the decision of a king or an emperor or
a queen that's how it was during the
mahajanapada republican era
and even during the time of lord krishna
during the mahabharata era you had a
similar system which was a democratic
system
right so democracy emerged out of india
it is native to india today's democracy
is nonsense it is a fake form of
democracy it is a it is a
illusory democracy the form of democracy
that we follow today is western liberal
democracy the westminster system of
parliamentary democracy which emerged
which which evolved on a small island
in the past the atlantic ocean england
right it is suited
to that country to that small island of
with the population of a few million
people
and in in the context of the
socio-political context that it evolved
in india is a whole different ball game
it is a subcontinent-sized civilization
a system that is suited for a small
island is not suitable for india and yet
it has been force forcefully imposed
upon india and you can see the result
look at the way the country has been
governed right now look at the
consequences look at where we find
ourselves today
india has reached nowhere near the
potential it had
we have had 70 years since independence
and see what
this
specific form of democracy so-called
democracy has done to the country india
is currently a corrupt
misgoverned third world country a very
poor nation our population is larger
than the entire continent of africa
our per capita gdp is lower than that of
bangladesh i am not blaming the current
government for this
it is something that has happened over
the past 70 years it is the fault of the
system
the the government system we have copied
from the west
the constitution we have copied from the
west and the laws
which were written by the british in
which we still follow
it is this colonial system that has
brought us to where we are so this fake
form of democracy is not suitable for
india we need to revisit our historical
past our civilizational eras when we
were doing when we were at the highest
levels of prosperity
and so on
and we need to try and replicate some of
that and at least be inspired from some
of that
and
find ways of replicating
such a system of governance in the 21st
century so i we should not try to
blindly follow or emulate what was there
in the past that was several thousand
years ago today we are in the 21st
century if we do
bring uh try to bring such a system back
it has to be
suitable it has to be
modified in a way that it
can work in the 21st century with all
the
technology and all that that we have
so that is what hopefully we need to do
that's the kind of governance governance
system v that is suitable for india
uh
constitution that is not foreign not
western but indian
in its nature in its characteristics it
is based on indian civilizational and
cultural values not western values not
this nonsense of secularism and so on
right
and the other question is when will the
partitioned land of bharata reunite
it will reunite when there is a great
great leader
who is capable of reuniting the country
and the civilization
so it's not going to happen in the next
50 years or 100 years because there's
too much cultural and religious
differences now in the lands that we
have lost so it's a long term project
but it will happen eventually if we
if we
ensure that the right kind of leadership
is allowed to rise to the top of the
country
okay let's take more questions
isha asks isha says my t my sister is a
history teacher how can she make
children learn real indian history while
the books teach
complete
well as a teacher unfortunately your
sister is duty bound to teach whatever
garbage the textbooks
contain that is
the contract that is
her job
and if she tries to teach something else
then she is going to be in trouble
so what can i say
your sister will have to teach
what is in the in the history textbooks
what she can do
is try and
motivate
the children
to look beyond the textbooks
that's what you can do
now that's very hard of course because
the the
in india's education system children
have very little spare time they have so
many subjects to study so much to
memorize blindly so much homework to do
then they have tuition classes coaching
classes they barely get to sleep eight
hours
so how will t how will children find the
time
when they don't even get time to play in
a playground how will they find the time
to read
some additional history
so that's the great unfortunate
challenge
that we have in this country today
the children in this country are put
under back breaking stress
so much homework so much school work
there's hardly any time to be a child to
be a kid and just play and enjoy your
life no you can't
so what can i say
that's where we are today
and they said that they are reforming
the education system what is it called
nep or something what absolute nonsense
we need real reforms children should not
be made to study more than three four
hours a day that's enough
instead of that they're studying all day
now
so that's the status of the indian
education system
what i would say is that
if she can somehow find a way to
motivate the children
to
to study some history to look at some
documentaries to read some books apart
from what they learn in class
in school
then maybe they'll be able to
learn
some of the real history of india
that's that's the best that we can do in
the
situation we are in right now
but yeah good question
aryan kumar says what if darashuko was
emperor instead of aaron zeb
well it's a hypothetical question maybe
he would have been a better person i
think aurangzeb was one of the one of
the worst tyrants to ever rule this
country one of the greatest monsters
to have existed anywhere in the world in
the past 1000 years
as bad as the european conquerors
of of the americas the kind of genocide
they did there even the new york times
agrees
that aurangzeb killed us italy how many
several million people in india
and whatever numbers they have given we
have to actually multiply that by ten to
come at the real figures so i think they
said the new york times estimates that
auraxed
was responsible for the genocide of
about five million indians i think
so if you multiply that by ten and you
reach
a number uh a figure of 50 million
indians so that must be the real figure
actually
so if darashigo was emperor instead of
aaron that most likely would not have
happened i think he was i think orex zeb
considered dharashuka to be a kafir
because he was very interested in indian
culture he learned sanskrit he
translated translated the either the
ramayana or the mahabharat or both
perhaps into persian
from sanskrit so he was a scholarly
person he wanted he was very interested
in indian language culture religion and
so on
and that's why aurangzeb hated him so
much and that's why he had him
murdered in such a cruel fashion and so
on
if darashuko was emperor instead of
aurangzeb maybe india
would have gone in a different direction
perhaps
but maybe he would not have been as
ruthless a ruler as aurangzeb and maybe
maybe
the marathas would have
would have re-conquered india from the
turks earlier perhaps
had darashiko been in power
so it's a hypothetical question maybe
india would have gone in a different
better
direction had he been the emperor
maybe something else would have happened
we can't really tell
but at least that massacre that genocide
that aurangzeb carried out would not
have happened so that would be one of
the most positive aspects
had darashiko prevailed instead of
aurangzeb
all right
more questions okay i had i had some
questions which i
picked up from the comments let me take
a few of those
a few of those questions let me take a
few of those
okay i'll need to remove this
all right
okay let me just take this question
atharva says can we restore the monarchy
of nepal
how is a hindu monarchy different from a
christian monarchy in europe or muslim
monarchies in the middle east
how will it be helpful for india
look nepal is today a separate country
it is not part of india so we in india
cannot restore the monarchy of nepal the
nepalese people will have to do it if
they so wish
now it looks it seems to me that the
people of nepal are now very much
pro-communist
the education system has as
has put certain ideas in the minds of
the younger people
and i i get the feeling that the younger
generations the newer generations the
new youngsters who you see online they
seem to be very much anti-india
anti-hindu some of them very much
pro-china and so forth so it looks quite
difficult for that sort of thing to
emerge from nepal itself unless
there is a significant percentage of
nepal's population that we are not aware
of that is in favor of restoring the
monarchy or restoring
hindu rule in nepal
but the communists hold all the power
they hold the power of the state the
guns everything so it's very hard to do
that it would be very hard to do that
how is a hindu monarchy different from a
christian monarchy or muslim monarchy
well the entire culture is different the
value system is different the system of
governance is different it is all ruled
and governed by
the principles and the values
of
of dharma of the dharmic culture and
that's that's why the entire value
system is different
and
the entire environment and culture is
different right
and so it would be more democratic more
uh
more compassionate and so on that's how
hindu monarchies are different from
various abrahamic systems
of governance
now if there's a hindu monarchy in nepal
how will it be helpful for india well if
there's a hindu monarchy they would be
more
inclined to resisting
the chinese attempts to
to bring nepal into
china's uh geopolitical sphere so in
that way it would be helpful for nepa
for for india
and it would be would be good for the
people of nepal as well
now it is india itself during mr rajiv
gandhi's time that it is india that
took steps clandestine covered steps
to
make the institution of monarchy in
nepal
weaker and weaker and eventually the
communists
were allowed to take over with help from
the indian government so it is india
itself
india's secular government
that destroyed nepal's hindu monarchy
so that's how it is
that's how it went
okay let me take a question from the
comments
so star cellars says
when scientists studied and
reconstructed the dna of king
tutankhamun in egypt
it was found that he carried the r1b
haplogroup as we know r1b branched out
of r1 a haplogroup and the yamnaya tribe
which carried r1b haplogroup invaded
europe
and spread that haplogroup across europe
it's also known that the egyptian
pharaohs practiced inbreeding to keep
the royal blood pure
so how can it be possible for king tut
to have r1b haplogroup
is it possible that the r1a haplogroup
originated in africa and then out of
africa migration brought it to india
okay that's a whole lot of questions yes
it is true that these this king this
pharaoh tutankhamun had the r1b
haplogroup the r1b haplogroup was
brought into europe by the yamana
invaders who rampaged across europe
about 5000 or 4500 years ago they were
indian in origin r1b did not branch out
of r1a r1b is a sister lineage of r1a
r1b and r1b r1a are daughter lineages of
r1
r1 is a daughter lineage of r and they
are all eventually
descendant lineages of the haplogroup f
which is the original haplogroup the
parent haplogroup of more than 90
of non-african males across the world
and the haplogroup f originated in india
so r1aron b did not originate in africa
they originated in india
and now how did
this guy tutankhamun happen to have the
r1b haplogroup so that's an interesting
question and that's not been
that that mystery has not been resolved
yet
what is clear is that he has
a haplogroup a petroleum lineage
that originated
in india
now how did it reach there how did it
enter into egypt i think today r1b is
extremely rare in egypt
less than one percent or two percent of
the population would have this
haplogroup in egypt
and yet egypt egypt's ancient royalty
had this patrilineal lineage which means
that they were descended from a male
who once lived in india but
between 18 and 26 or so thousand years
before today
so isn't that interesting we don't know
really why or how come this haplogroup
ended up in
in egypt's royalty so that is a question
that has not been answered yet i think
it is something that researchers are
looking into but as of today we don't
have the answer
but interesting very interesting
question
right
okay this is this is by lkjk whatever
that is
what are your views on the nasa sukta of
the rig veda
don't you think that the nasa diya sukta
is blasphemous
as it doubts the capability of god
because that sukkah essentially says
that even god does not know everything
wow
good question let okay what is the nasa
it is the creation him in the rigveda
so the rig veda is the
oldest known literature
in human history
it is
the
foundational
text of india's civilization
what we call hinduism and dharma dharma
originates
from the rigveda which is the oldest
text in the dharmic world in the entire
human world
so what is the nasa descriptor let me
just share the screen with you
now
i have i have said this before i will
say it again wikipedia is not a reliable
source of information i am doing this
just for convenience for this once
but please do not trust wikipedia in
this case i have seen this and it seems
to be fine so this is the nasa desktop
and here's the translation let us begin
with the first stanza paragraph
okay so it it it is it it concerns the
origin
of the universe the creation of the
universe this particular him deals with
the creation of the universe the
question of where did the universe come
from who created it so it says that in
the beginning
even non-existence was not there
and
neither was existence
there was no air there was no space
what covered it where was it in who's
keeping
was there then cosmic fluid
in depths unfathomed
there was neither death death nor
immortality there was neither night or
day
the one breathed windlessly and
self-sustaining
there was that one then and there was no
other
there was only darkness wrapped in
darkness
only
unilumined cosmic water
and so on and so forth
and then it says after all who knows and
who can say
where did it all come from
and how did creation happen
the gods themselves are later than
creation
so who knows truly from where it has
arisen
from where did creation have its origin
the creator whether he made it or maybe
he did not
the creator who surveys it from the
highest heaven
he knows
or maybe even he does not know
so this is the nasa
it talks about creation it asks the
question see many people have asked me
this question in the past
what was there before the big bang
what caused the big bang
isn't it
asks the same questions
who caused creation the creation of the
universe
where did
this creation happen from
what was there before the big bang
before the creation of the universe
this singularity that we talk about
where was it
in what was it contained and so on and
so forth these are the same questions
that are asked in the nasda
it says
that even the gods came after the
creation of the universe because gods
are part of the universe
so who created the universe and
it doesn't answer the question it simply
raises the questions
and it says even the gods don't know
even the gods came later this is a very
skeptical very agnostic
portion
a very agnostic view
a very scientific view in a sense
because science is all about agnosticism
and skepticism we don't know what really
happened
right we can't tell and that is
the creation hymn of the rigveda
so yes
it does raise into question whether god
exists or not who is god who create who
is the creator of the universe and it
says we don't know we don't know it
doesn't give you an answer
so that's why the question has been
asked that
is this blasphemous as it doubts the
capability of god or the existence of
god
so he what is blasphemy what is the
definition of blasphemy the definition
of blasphemy is that you
deny the existence
of god
you
deny the truth that is contained in the
one book and in the words of your
prophet so blasphemy is an abrahamic
concept
when you say that what the so-called
prophet has said is wrong you are being
blasphemous when you deny the truth of
what is written in that one book
then you are doing blasphemy when you
say that this god that you are supposed
to pray to doesn't exist you are doing
blasphemy now in the dharmic world
there is no such thing as blasphemy
because the foundational text of
dharma the rigveda is itself expressing
an agnostic view that we don't know
about creation we don't know who created
the universe we don't know who god is
so if there is a holy text
in hinduism
there are so many holy texts there are
so many openishads and puranas and vedas
and such an enormous corpus of
literature but among all of this the
holiest of the texts is the rig veda
so if you were to deny what is in the
rigveda that is blasphemy the rig veda
cannot be a blasphemous text it is the
holiest of texts and again like i said
there is no such thing as blasphemy in
hinduism in dharma for instance in the
dharmic
philosophies
there are many philosophies that
question the existence of god charvaka
philosophy for instance it says that
perception is the only valid source of
knowledge the material world is the only
reality and god is a myth
right charvaka says that it is part of
dharma
jaina philosophy also rejects the
existence of god
both the philosophy also exists uh also
rejects the existence of god it says
that soul does exist but god doesn't
exist the niyah philosophy says that god
exists
it also says atma exists vaishashik's
philosophy says that god exists
right the sankhya philosophy
doesn't see any need for god it says
there are two realities purus and
prakruthi the yoga philosophy is a
theistic sankhya it says that god exists
the me mansa philosophy says there is no
supreme soul or creator god it is very
skeptical again and the vedanta
philosophy which arises from the open
asians says that there is a supreme
person who permeates the entire universe
and yet remains beyond it so that kind
of echoes
the nasa
so there are so many different views in
dharma there is no blasphemy if you say
that god doesn't exist or if you
question
the origin of the universe or the
existence of god if you are skeptical
you have the right to be skeptical you
will not be thrown of a building so
essentially what i would like to say is
that the answer is that there is no such
thing as blasphemy in hinduism all
opinions are equally valid all opinions
are respected you may believe in atheism
fine that's your life go on and live it
that's how it is there is no such thing
as blasphemy and the only thing i would
consider to be blasphemous is
questioning the rig veda
that itself is the highest if if
blasphemy if anything is to be
considered blasphemous in hinduism in
dharma
then that would be questioning the
rigveda itself which is what this
question does actually
isn't that funny
okay next question
this is about the kailash mountain if
this mountain was an indian territory i
am sure there would have been many
people ready to somehow climb it to hurt
the sentiments of the hindus and so on
and so forth
so i had
answered a question in the past in one
of the previous episodes
about mount kailash it is currently
illegally occupied by china it is under
chinese territory under chinese
occupation and the chinese communist
party has prohibited anybody from trying
to climb this mountain
so
so this
comment says that if the mountain was in
indian territory
i am sure there would have been many
people ready to climb it somehow to hurt
the sentiments of hindus i agree with
you
if this mountain was in indian territory
if it was administered by india
then there would have been many public
interest legitimations
litigations litigations in the supreme
court pils etc from various ngos and
secular organizations
asking the supreme court to make it
legal
for people to climb the mountain
and there would have been many attempts
to climb the mountain
and the supreme court would definitely
have made it
a would have definitely ordered the
government to allow the climbing of this
mountain so you know what it's so
strange that i have to say this but i
agree with you i think it is actually
good
that while india is ruled by the secular
foreign constitution and the secular
foreign
government system machinery
while we are in under this condition i
think it's actually good
strangely
that the mountain is currently
administered by china
because they will not allow it to be
climbed
if it was under indian jurisdiction by
now all kinds of people would have tried
climbing it they would have defiled and
desecrated this holy mountain so i'm
glad that's not happened isn't that
ridiculous
the kind of country we're living in
today
incredible
ashutosh says i read an interesting
article today that many of the corrupt
african politicians
their wealth is on par with people like
bill gates warren buffett etc any
thoughts on this
yes i agree i haven't read the article
but it's very much possible that despite
these countries being so extremely poor
their rulers their politicians
they may have wealth on par with people
like bill gates buffett etc
and all of their wealth would be stashed
away in
in some european or western countries
for instance many of these afghan
politicians who escaped from afghanistan
taliban took over
they are billionaires they have
incredible amounts of wealth stashed
away in western banks
yes afghanistan shows that
and let's talk about india
i can guarantee that certain indian
politicians
are actually the richest people in the
world
i do not doubt that at all
i think some indian politicians would
have more wealth than the richest man in
the world or woman in the world
i don't know who they would be i mean
i'm sure you can guess i'm sure even i
can guess but
i am not taking any names
but i think india goes way beyond these
african dictators and politicians
we are the country that is the most
corrupt in the world and we have been so
since independence before that
since the foreign occupation of india
and much of this country's wealth has
been amassed by these illicit
corrupt politicians i think indian
politicians some of them would be richer
than the richest officially designed
designated person in the world
and that is terrible
says why didn't the british loot the
treasure of the ananta padmanabhaswami
temple in kerala which is worth
trillions of dollars in today's wealth
what
prevented them from doing so
this is a very good question
in the past my friends
i have been extremely critical
extremely critical
of india's so-called princely states and
these rulers
i have
said that these people these princely
states and their petty little rulers
they were puppets of the british
and they did everything the british told
them to do they danced to the to the
tunes of the british
now hear me out
the royal family of travancore are one
of the princely states they they were
puppets of the british they had a
british political agent who told them
what to do and they had to take orders
from the british political agents and
they had to allow the british
like every other princely state
to govern their kingdom
and tax their people like every other
puppet kingdom in india
and yet
the royal family of travancore
did not ever allow the british
to get wind of the fact
that that ananta padmanabhaswamy temple
is the richest temple in the history of
humanity
the british never came to know about
this
so this royal family the royal family of
travancore
safeguarded the wealth of our ancestors
the wealth of our ancestors and people
from god knows where
had donated to this temple over
thousands of years
and that's why this temple is currently
the richest temple in the world worth
trillions of dollars in today's wealth
and i am so glad that i recently heard
that the supreme court of india
strangely enough and thankfully enough i
really appreciate it
they
ruled that
it is the travancore royal family who
will administer the wealth of this
temple and nobody else not the
government of kerala
if this wealth had fallen into the hands
of the government the secular government
end of story politicians will get richer
so
it is all thanks to this royal family
this princely royal family travancore
royal family
that india
was able
at least this particular
temple
was saved
from the depredations and the plunder
of these
rapacious british
occupiers of india
it is all thanks to the travancore royal
family
so the moral of the story is that even
though each of all of these princely
states were puppets of the british some
of them still had some integrity and
some of them
did not forget
that the highest morality of the ruler
is to serve the country and the people
as per the great acharya vishnu gupta
chanakya
so i am very grateful to the royal
family of travancore i have the highest
amount of respect and gratitude for them
and now we go back to live questions
okay some live questions let's see what
do we have
inquisitive triangulator says is it true
that present day hinduism is made up of
64 different religions in ancient bharat
my teacher said this but i could not
find it anywhere in the internet
buffering
well i don't know what your teacher is
smoking i don't want any of that
there is no such thing as religion
in indian culture or civilization
religion
is a western abrahamic concept
hinduism itself this name this term
hinduism
is a foreign term
the correct term is dharma
so india's culture is dharma it's it's
the dharmic culture
the precepts of dharma is what makes up
india's culture and it is now called
hinduism there are no religions in
hinduism there are different
philosophies
i just mentioned a number of these
philosophies right
vedanta yoga etc
these are different philosophical
schools of thought very some of them are
very different from each other
some of them are quite similar and so on
and so forth and there are many more
so these are not religions these are
philosophical schools of thought and all
of this combined including jaina and
boda
this all of this it makes up
dharma the dharmic
world view which is very diverse
very pluralistic
atheism is very much a part of it some
of it is atheistic like jaina
like buddha
like charvaka
even mansa is kind of like that it is
kind of atheistic it says there is no
supreme soul or creator god and then
there is very much
like vedanta etc very much believes in
the existence of god and there are many
other philosophical schools of thought
that are not that uh
notable but did exist and so on so i
would say there are there have been
hundreds
of different
world views within
the overarching umbrella of dharmic
culture and dharmic philosophy and the
dharmic world view
so
i don't know what 64 different religions
your teacher was referring to but that
is certainly
not the case
india
is a very very complex
pluralistic civilization but at the very
core of it is the four vedas and the
oldest one is the rigveda and that's
where everything springs for from
springs forth from emerges from
all right
let's take some more questions
surjit says what do you think would be
the future of taiwan with china
constantly threatening them
and the great world powers including the
us not supporting them what effects
would it have on india
well the chinese seem to be doing dress
rehearsals for an eventual
invasion of taiwan as we speak today
in october 2021 recently there was a big
large-scale incursion of chinese
aircraft into taiwanese airspace 64
chinese aircraft intruded into taiwanese
airspace
so they are pushing the envelope of what
is acceptable they're pushing the
boundary of what's acceptable they are
they are every day trying to create a
new normal
and they seem to be doing doing dry runs
and test rehearsals of an eventual
invasion of taiwan yes it is definitely
it does definitely look
like that is the case
now
will the u.s not support taiwan i think
it's very unlikely that the us will not
support taiwan if the chinese are
allowed to take over taiwan then the u.s
will
be seen as have lost a great amount of
face and the entire american credibility
will evaporate overnight if the chinese
are available
are allowed
to take taiwan over and conquer taiwan
without any resistance
so the americans will not allow that to
happen if they allow it to happen their
entire credibility will evaporate
overnight
because they are seen they have
officially guaranteed
the security of other countries as well
south korea
japan
and other countries
as well
so if the americans don't safeguard the
sovereignty of taiwan then the japanese
will no longer trust them that south
koreans will not no longer trust them
the entire global system that they have
created the so-called rules-based system
will
overnight
become untenable so the americans will
have to support taiwan and the chinese
will not invade taiwan until they are
convinced
until they are 100 sure of victory
and right now they are not 100 sure of
winning such an invasion and that's why
they are simply trying to push the
envelope and
keep on doing these incursions i think
an invasion of taiwan could happen betw
within the next
five to ten years
and what effect will it have on india
see if china successfully invades taiwan
and reunifies like it says
this renegade province like it claims it
to be
then china will become way more powerful
right with this great success and way
more confident and that will be bad for
india because the chinese the chinese
have been claiming indian territory as
well for a long time
including arunachal pradesh which is a
significant
land mass isn't it
so it would be very bad for india so
what should india do if china
invades taiwan india should immediately
without wasting a single hour
move militarily to secure nepal bhutan
and sri lanka
how to do it well the government should
decide how to do it best i think the
military should be involved in this and
there should be not a moment's delay if
china decides to invade taiwan
because it would have a very bad effect
on india so india would needs to be very
proactive
if such a thing happens right
so there's your answer surjit thank you
for the question
okay tanveer singh says
what are your views on china interfering
in afghanistan do you think it's going
to fail like the ussr in the u.s as it
is called the graveyard of empires
see the british called afghanistan the
graveyard of empires uh
it has always been
the place where european powers have
failed western powers have failed
for instance this guy uh the greek
fellow what's his name alexander
he tried to invade india afghanistan was
then part of india the invasion was a
disaster it cost alexander his life
so you could say that it ended up being
the graveyard of the greek
empire of alexander
later on the british tried to invade
afghanistan
and subdue the locals they failed
disastrously
then the ussr
tried that they also failed and that's
why and now the americans have also
withdrawn without achieving any real
objective
their their original objective was to
defeat the taliban well the taliban are
back in power so the greeks failed the
soviets failed the british failed and
the americans have failed so that's why
it's called the graveyard of empires but
it's only been the graveyard of western
empires right because the turks did
invade afghanistan gandhar
and they did conquer it and to change
the entire
culture and demographics and religion of
the place it was a hindu buddhist land
it was an indian
province in indian territory today it's
a separate country so the turks
succeeded in their invasion of
afghanistan and they
transformed
and changed the demographics permanently
right
so the turkic empire did not fail
now the chinese interference and
acquisition what that's what they have
always wanted to do they want to expand
their geopolitical footprint they want
to turn afghanistan into one of the uh
transit points of their
belt and road infrastructure
right
and they also want to extract the
natural resources the minerals etc from
afghanistan copper various rare earth
minerals and so on and so forth
and they also want to ensure the
stability of the taliban government
government in afghanistan so that
the taliban sentiment doesn't spill over
into chinese occupied east turkestan or
xinjiang
so these are the reasons why the chinese
are currently involved in afghanistan
that's why they are uh
cooperating with the taliban government
and helping them
to in in a variety of ways
so that's what they are doing now will
they succeed will they fail the
americans would want them to fail
many geopolitical analysts have opined
that
the american withdrawal from afghanistan
is actually a trap for china
they want china to get
embroiled in the situation there and
bogged in and eventually they want the
chinese to suffer a disastrous defeat
the way the ussr suffered some 30 or so
years ago
will that happen it all depends on the
chinese
what kind of uh playbook do they
adopt the chinese are not stupid they're
not foolish they know what the americans
are planning they know what the
americans are hoping for
and they will have learned the lessons
of history from the soviet disaster in
afghanistan so
it all depends on our variety of factors
on a variety of factors the taliban
government how long will they last what
sort of relationship will they have with
the pakistanis
will pass through nationalism
override
pakistan's attempts to
control
the taliban leadership and so on and so
forth
there's a lot there's a lot at stake
here there's a lot of factors at play
it's a complicated environment
and the answers to these questions will
be visible in the next five to ten years
it's right now too early to say what's
going to happen
but i see that
things will not quite go according to
what the chinese have planned or even
according to what the pakistanis have
planned
this could actually
if certain cards are played right it
could actually
excuse me
it could potentially be the beginning of
the end for pakistan it could
so let's see how things go but
uh it's it's it's very early days like
in cricket and test matches on the first
day you can't tell how things are going
to go so we're in that sort of situation
right now
so it's too early to tell but yeah it is
certainly a possibility that the chinese
plants and the pakistanis plants will
not quite
go the way they want
them to go
all right let's see some more questions
says what are my thoughts on the james
webb telescope will it be able to find
life on other exoplanets it is possible
yes
so i believe this telescope is going to
be launched soon it's been in the works
for almost two decades maybe more lots
of delays lots of delays so this
telescope is going to
replace the hubble space telescope it's
going to be several or i think at least
an order of magnitude more powerful than
the hubble space telescope it's going to
allow us to see much further much deeper
into the cosmos
and i believe that yes one could
actually be able to view exoplanets and
possibly find signatures of life
therein
so yes it's going to be a significant
leap forward when it comes to comes to
observational
astronomy astrophysics and all that it's
going to be
a very exciting period in time
in this discipline
will we be definitively able to find
life on exoplanets we can't say for sure
we will i think definitely be able to
capture images of exoplanets
much better than we are able to right
now we have already been able to take
visible light images
of a planet
around another star
now this is going to be this ability
this capability will be significantly
augmented with the james webb telescope
and
so we will have significantly more
powerful capabilities when it comes to
life it is still not known if we will be
able to find life but if life does exist
i think sooner or later we will find it
at least somewhere as long as we look
look it up
right
let's see some questions
shivam goyal says
do you see a civil war happening in
india in the coming 10 to 15 years
looking at how the situation is shaping
it all depends on the on the government
and the leadership
uh
india is currently
kind of a soft state
there are so many protests happening and
law and order is a state issue so you
leave it to the state and you know every
state has its own agenda
so i'm not naming any specific state i'm
just saying overall
you know a big picture comment so yeah
there are many problems going on ntca
protests and farmer alleged farmer
protests and
various other things
various places various parts of the
country yeah it does look like a civil
war is a possibility
there is so much foreign infiltration
into india rohingyas and bangladesh's
i think there could be more than 10
million illegal bangladesh living in
india with with
with all the
original paperwork like other cards and
what not you know
so it's a situation that's not very
very good
will there be a civil war it's a
possibility it all depends
on the leadership and on the government
if you have the right leadership there
will be there will never be a civil war
if you have weak leadership you will
have civil wars everywhere
so it all depends on how strong the
state is the central government is and
the local states also
india's federal system is very weak
there's too much power
in the hands of each state
and that is something that needs to be
reformed in my opinion so this is
something that needs to be taken up
seriously with
a certain amount of urgency i would say
but i am helpful i am hopeful
that there will be no civil war
the the
uh the seeds
of of a civil war are certainly there in
the country
they have been there since the 1940s
since 1947 since the events of 1947 the
seeds of a future civil war the seeds of
demand for more partitions are there in
the country for sure
so it all depends on the leadership
what kind of leaders are we going to
have in this country
what kind of
leader are we going to elect in this
country which political party will we
elect
it all depends on that
if we make the right choices we will
have good good leaders strong leaders
and there won't be a civil war otherwise
yes
there could be a civil war like
situation in the next 10 15 years two
years 20 years possibly
it all depends on these factors
[Laughter]
arkadar says tell us something about
love relationship breakups
i think you're asking the wrong person
that is i
relationship advice and all that's
that's not what i do
uh
that's not my specialty or or
or forte so
i'm sure there are many other channels
where you can ask these questions you
know
people who give dating advice
relationship advice
and so on breakups
and all that
so yeah i am sorry i apologize but i
don't have the answer to this
this is not something that you know i i
don't believe in giving personal advice
to people your love life your
relationship life etc is your personal
it's it's a personal thing it's a
private thing i don't interfere in
people's lives
i respect your privacy
and uh
and i i don't
like to give advice in in these personal
matters you know
so
so sorry i apologize there are plenty of
other people who will be very happy to
give such advice
right
okay let's take a couple more questions
okay let's see some more
tanmay asks will a military coup take
place in pakistan is there is a spat
between
bajwa the chief of the army and imran
khan who is the
so-called prime minister of pakistan
there's always the possibility of a
military coup in pakistan it can happen
anytime as long as the prime minister
tows the line that the army tells him to
he's going to be fine
as long as he is useful to the army they
will allow him to be in power
and the moment he becomes intransigent
or
uncooperative
or a little bit too independent-minded
then it will be quietly replaced or not
so quietly replaced
so sometimes you may have a coup which
doesn't even look like a coup it just
looks like an election result
for instance if there is this widespread
allegation in pakistan that the
last
election
was rigged by the army
and they ensured that imran khan came to
power
actually maybe nawaz sharif would have
won if there was no rigging and so on so
forth it's an allegation that many
people have made
so
is it possible it is certainly possible
pakistan is not a democracy it's a
it's an army run dictatorship that's
what it is the prime minister is just
for sure just to keep the west mollified
and just to keep up appearances imran
khan has no real power
he is just a puppet
so it is possible
the moment he becomes incredible the
moment he becomes
a little too independent
he will be dealt with by the army
okay path sharma says my teacher said
that chanakya is fictional there are no
archaeological evidences of him
and he only appears on texts after
mauryan rule
well who wrote that book
the arthashastra
there are so many historical figures for
whom there is no archaeological evidence
i mean mr christ
jesus christ is there any archaeological
evidence of him and yet every history
teacher will talk to you about mr christ
there are millions of books written
about jesus christ
right but the same
but but
and yet those rules don't apply to
indian historical figures
right
so that's the thing right
uh they will apply one set of rules to
historical figures from the west even
those that don't that have never existed
but they'll apply a completely different
set of rules to indian historical
figures and
india's
teachers and academics are so
brainwashed that we don't even need the
westerners to do this we do it ourselves
now our own teachers will come and raise
questions about all our historical
figures so my advice is just ignore such
individuals
in india we are taught that our teachers
are our gurus and we have to worship
them utter nonsense
our teachers
your teacher will refuse to teach you
the moment you stop paying him or her
our teachers today are merely service
providers they are not gurus
there's an enormous difference between
the gurus of old
and today's teachers
gurus used to impart education
without asking for money in return the
guru dakshina was completely voluntary
it was only a once in a lifetime thing
after you
became successful and you became
financially independent then you had the
option of offering a one
one time
once in a lifetime
fee or payment anything that you
yourself wish to give
there was no monthly guru dakshina with
10 percent off if you pay annually and
all that nonsense
gurus were supported by the with the
state
and not everybody called could be called
a guru
you could you would be you would be
given the title of a guru only if you if
you rose to a certain amount of
intellectual excellence
right so so our our teachers are not
gurus they are merely service providers
most of them are mediocre most of them
know nothing about education or about
anything about our history most of them
are
have very shallow and superficial
knowledge so my advice to all of you is
that do not take your teachers seriously
you have to go through the education
system to get your degrees go through it
get your degrees don't pay too much
attention to what your teacher said
don't take it very seriously when they
raise questions about india's historical
figures and don't believe the history
that you have you are forced to memorize
memorize it
write your answers in the exam and then
forget it then when you get the time
learn the real history of india which is
very different
from what's being
taught
all right my friends i think we have
reached the end of today's session it's
nearly two hours
i can see lots more questions i
apologize to all of you
it's simply impossible for me to take
all of your questions my uh
what i would like to say to uh
to the new viewers to the new
subscribers is that i have
more than 500 videos on my channel on
this channel it's all questions that i
have answered in the past and i have
many of these live streams 50 50
more live streams that i've done in the
past i have answered hundreds of
questions in these live streams so in
case i am not able to answer your
question
then please go go to my channel use the
search function and search for what for
the question that you have most likely
it may already have been answered
so please go through the channel
to look for questions if you have any
right
all right thank you so much guys girls
ladies gentlemen friends thank you very
much for the questions
thank you for your viewership i will see
you again tomorrow tomorrow is a video
chat
uh episode so i will see you then
until then thank you very much take care
good day good night
bye